<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The humble petition of the Lord Major, aldermen, and commons of the City of London in Common-Councell assembled. To the Right Honourable the Lords and Commons assembled in High Court of Parliament. With their answer to the said petition.</title>
            <author>City of London (England). Court of Common Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86810</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3535</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E396_15</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201651</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862151</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862151</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114300</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86810)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114300)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 63:E396[15])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The humble petition of the Lord Major, aldermen, and commons of the City of London in Common-Councell assembled. To the Right Honourable the Lords and Commons assembled in High Court of Parliament. With their answer to the said petition.</title>
                  <author>City of London (England). Court of Common Council.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 9, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Cotes, printer to the Honourable City of London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>On the disbandment of the army.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 3d".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114300:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 7 -->
            <p>The humble PETITION OF THE Lord Major, Aldermen, and Commons of
the City of <hi>LONDON</hi> in Common-Councell aſſembled. TO THE Right
Honourable the Lords and Commons aſſembled in High Court OF
<hi>PARLIAMENT.</hi> With their Anſwer to the ſaid Petition.</p>
            <p>Printed by <hi>Richard Cotes,</hi> Printer to the Honorable City
of <hi>London,</hi> 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:114300:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 8 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114300:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 8 -->
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable the Lords and Commons aſſembled
in High Court OF PARLIAMENT; <hi>The humble Petition of the Lord Major,
Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Commons of the City of</hi> London <hi>in Common-Councell
aſſembled;</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>Humbly ſheweth,</opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the Petitioners cannot but call to minde the deliverance,
which they and the whole Kingdome did juſtly expect from this Parliament,
after ſo many yeares ſuffering under the power of an arbitrary Government,
both in their ſpirituall and temporall concernments; and they doe humbly
acknowledge that this Parliament hath removed many obſtacles, and are
confident, would by this time, with Gods bleſſing, have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored the
Kingdome to its juſt liberties, and ſetled a ſure foundation for its
future happineſſe, if they had not beene diverted by the great contrivers
of the Kingdomes ſlavery, who, rather then ſubmit to the juſtice of this
High Court, <pb n="2" facs="tcp:114300:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 9 -->have raiſed,
maintained, and continued a bloody unnaturall and long Warre againſt the
Parliament of <hi>England.</hi> In the ſuppreſſion whereof, as much blood
hath been ſpilt, ſo a great Treaſure hath beene ſpent, and the Kingdome
is ſtill left involved in many engagements and debts, both to their Brethren
of <hi>Scotland</hi> (who like true Chriſtian Brethren came in to its ayde
againſt the common enemy) and alſo to a multitude of Officers, Souldiers,
and others the well affected people of this Land, who did ingage in the defence
and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port thereof. And although the Petitioners in the obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which
the cauſe of God, and the publique ſafetie did caſt upon them, have all
this time both freely contributed, and cheerfully ſubmitted to many great and
unuſuall Aſſeſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which alſo could not bee leavied but in an
extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary way, yet they cannot bee unſenſible, how much arbitrary
power hath beene, during theſe diſtempers, exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed by Committees and
others, by whom the good Subject hath beene oftentimes more oppreſſed, then
the Delinquent ſuppreſſed, and who have managed the Receipts and
Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues which were deſigned to maintaine the publique charge, ſo
diſorderly and ineffectually, that the Kingdome cannot but bee unſatisfied
concerning the due imployment thereof, and doubt that much of the publique
Money hath beene imployed to private ends, and remaine obſcured in the hands
of ſuch as were intruſted with the Collection of thoſe
Aſſeſſements, and the improvement of all Sequeſtrations to the
publique and beſt advantage. And indeed the Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners have reaſon to
attribute much of the late diſcontent and diſorders of divers Officers and
Souldiers, unto the want of ſuch Moneys, as if duely collected and faithfully
managed, might have in good part, If not fully, ſatisfied the Souldiery; And
doe humbly conceive, that the Parliament hath ſo much the more reaſon to
enquire into the ſame, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that from this defect, hath riſen thoſe
late Attempts of ſome of the Souldiery, and there is ſuch uſe made of the
Vote paſſed by the Parliament for their ſatisfaction, to invite and draw
together very great numbers of Officers and Souldiers from all parts of the
Kingdome, under pretence <pb n="3" facs="tcp:114300:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 9 -->of
ſharing the money ſo obtained, that it may very much indanger the peace and
ſafetie of the Citie.</p>
            <p>The Petitioners therefore for remedy of the ſaid Grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
and prevention of thoſe dangers which otherwiſe may bee feared, and for
ſettlement of this miſerable and diſtracted kingdome, doe humbly pray,</p>
            <p>I. That preſent command bee given that no Officer of Warre or
Souldier, other then ſuch as are already come in, doe enter the Line of
Communication, under any pretence to ſhare in the Moneys lately appointed by
Parliament, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſatisfaction of any Arreares.</p>
            <p>II. That ſuch Officers and Souldiers who are already paid
according to the late ſeverall Ordinances of Parliament in this behalfe made,
if their uſuall habitation and imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have beene within the Line, bee
enjoyned forthwith to betake themſelves to their calling, or ſome honeſt
condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of living, and bee prohibited from their looſer and tumultuous
wandring and meeting within this Citie, and other places adjacent, under
penaltie of loſing their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reares. And that ſuch Officers and Souldiers as
have dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings or other relations in the Countrey, bee required to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part the
Line within two dayes after publication, and to returne to their homes or
habitations, and there to apply themſelves to their ſeverall callings, upon
the like forfeiture of their Arreares, except ſuch whoſe preſent and
lawfull oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions may require their continuance, to bee approved of by a
Committee for that purpoſe to be appointed. And that the Parliament would
pleaſe to make ſome ſpeedy and certaine proviſion for the ſatisfying
of all Arrears unto the Souldiery, who have ſerved the Parliament, within
ſome ſhort and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient time to bee paid in the ſeverall Counties and
Places of their abode, according to the conditions of their
enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement.</p>
            <p>III. That all Officers and Souldiers who have beene in Armes
againſt the Parliament, or others who have aſſiſted or contributed
thereunto, bee injoyned upon paine of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment within 24. houres after
publication to repaire to their ſeverall habitations, and fall to their
lawfull cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings; <pb n="4" facs="tcp:114300:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->And that
ſuch Officers, Souldiers, and others as have no habitations neerer, be
commanded forthwith to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw themſelves and to continue at leaſt
twentie miles from <hi>London,</hi> for the ſpace of fortie dayes; Except
ſuch as by a Committee authorized and appointed to that purpoſe ſhall
have licence, upon juſt cauſe, by them allowed, to remaine in or neere
<hi>London</hi> ſo long time, untill they have diſpatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſuch
buſineſſes as they ſhall have in or neare the Citie; which ended, then
preſently to retire twentie miles from the Citie upon paine of impriſonment
as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>IV. That ſuch Commanders and Souldiers as, according to former
orders of the Parliament, have come in from the Army having received their
Moneys, may bee otherwiſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of as the Parliament ſhall thinke
fit.</p>
            <p>V. That all perſons whatſoever that are poſſeſſed of
any Moneys or Goods belonging to the Publick, may be injoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to bring the
ſame, within one month after publication, into ſuch publike Treaſury as
is or ſhall be appointed for that purpoſe, under penalty to forfeit treble
the value, which ſhall be duely proved to be ſo concealed, the halfe of the
for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture to be given to ſuch perſons as ſhall make proofe of ſuch
concealment, and the other halfe to be applyed to the ſervice of the
State.</p>
            <p>VI. That all Revenues as well ſuch as are due by
Seque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration as otherwiſe, be managed under ſuch Commiſſions, and
by ſuch Perſons as notwithſtanding any Priviledge of Parliament or
otherwiſe, may be held to ſuch Rules as are or ſhall be preſcribed
therein, by Ordinance of Parliament, and be lyable for breach thereof, to
anſwer the ſame in due courſe of Law; and that no arbitrary power may be
exerciſed to the contrary by any perſon whatſoever.</p>
            <p>VII. That the Parliament would for preſent pleaſe to lay
aſide all buſineſſes of leſſer conſequence or private
concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and improve their time and utmoſt endeavour, that ſuch Lawes
may be prepared for His Majeſties Royall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence, as may ſettle the
Government of the Church, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the People from all unlawfull and arbitrary
power what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever in future, and reſtore his Majeſty to His juſt Rights
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114300:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->and Authority, according to the
Covenant, without all which the Petitioners can never expect any laſting
eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. That ſo this long divided and diſtracted Kingdome may
attaine to the Bleſſings of Peace and Unity in Church and Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>VIII. And that the People may be the better ſecured to enjoy
the intended effects of ſuch Lawes as ſhall be ſo made with the Royall
aſſent, That eſpeciall care be taken that all Officers of State, and
other Miniſters of Juſtice, may bee Perſons of Honour, of conſiderable
Intereſt and of known Integrity to the Parliament and Kingdome.</p>
            <p>IX. That the Parliament would pleaſe to provide for the
carrying on of the affaires in <hi>Ireland</hi> by ſpeedy tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting the
Forces which ly ready on the Sea ſide, and ſuch others as ſhall be
willing to engage in that ſervice, and by ſuch continuall ſupplies as are
requiſite to reduce that Kingdome to the obedience of the Crowne of
<hi>England,</hi> and reſcue the good party left there, out of the bloudy
hands of thoſe bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous rebells. And for the better incouragement of the
Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of this Kingdome to continue their ſupplies for that Service, that
with as much ſpeed as conveniently may bee, the Parliament will pleaſe to
take care that the People be eaſed of ſuch extraordinary charges and
burthens as have long layne and ſtill remaine upon this Kingdom.</p>
            <p>X. That by all juſt and good means the correſpondence with
our Brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi> may, according to the Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Covenant, be
maintained and preſerved.</p>
            <p>XI. That this Honourable Houſe would pleaſe to give or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
for a ſpeedy examination of all unlawfull Elections and Returns of the
Members thereof, and purge the Houſe of all ſuch as have bin unduely
choſen, or have bin in Armes or in action againſt the Parliament, and
provide for the ſupply of their roomes according to the Lawes of the
Land.</p>
            <p>XII. That ſome ſpeedy courſe may be taken for the
deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of all cauſes formerly determinable in the Court of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miralty, the
Trade and Navigation of this Kingdome, and the correſpondence with Forraign
Nations, being very much prejudiced, diſturbed and indangered for want of due
Proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <pb n="6" facs="tcp:114300:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->herein, as hath
formerly been at large repreſented unto this Honourable Houſe.</p>
            <p>XIII. And laſtly, That ſatisfaction being made by
De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents, according to the wiſedome of Parliament, an Act of
<hi>Oblivion</hi> may be paſſed for an utter abolition and finall
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concilement of all Parties and Differences, and for the quiet ſetling of
Peace, Love, and Unitie, among the Subjects of this Kingdome.</p>
            <p>All which the Petitioners ſubmit unto the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of this
Honourable Houſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:114300:5"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->
            <head>Die Veneris, 2. Julii, 1647.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat their Lordſhips have had a long experience of the good
affections of the City of London to the Parliament and Kingdome, and they do
return their acknowledgement for the ſame. As to the particulars of the
Petition, which are many and long, they will take them into their ſpeedy
conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Jo. Browne Cler.
Parliamentorum.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:114300:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
            <head>Die Veneris, 2. Julii, 1647.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Houſe being informed, That the Sheriffes, and divers
Citizens of the City of <hi>London</hi> were at the Doore, they were called in,
and Sheriffe <hi>Edmonds</hi> informed the Houſe, That he was commanded by
the Lord Major, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen, and Commons in Common-Councell aſſembled, to
deliver a Petition to this Houſe; the which (the Petitioners being withdrawn)
was read.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſolved &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That on Fryday next, this Petition be read and conſidered
of.</p>
            <p>The Petitioners were again called in, and Mr. Speaker by the
Command of the Houſe acquainted them, that the Petition conſiſted of many
Heads of great and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like concernment, That moſt of them 
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114300:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->were under conſideration with
the Houſe.</p>
            <p>That their conſtant very good affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons did ſtill appeare,
for which he was commanded to render them thanks; he further acquainted them,
that the Houſe has appointed a day for the reading and conſidering of this
Petition.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>H. Elſynge Cler. Parl. D.
Com.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
